Ernest John Swift Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Ernest John Swift Papers 1908-2019 (bulk 1920-1941)
MSS 86310
Swift, Ernest John
1,500 items
6 containers plus 1 oversize
2.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
American Red Cross official. Correspondence, newspaper clippings, awards, photographs, and publications relating to Swift's career with the Red Cross from 1920 to 1941, as well as his personal and family life.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Swift family.; Swift, Ernest John.
Organizations
American Red Cross.; International Conference of the Red Cross (15th: 1934: Tokyo, Japan); Stanford University--Students.
Subjects
Humanitarian assistance.; International relief.
Places
India--Description and travel.; Japan--Description and travel.
Occupations
American Red Cross officials.
Provenance
The papers of Ernest John Swift were given to the Library of Congress by Paul D. Cronin in 2019.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Ernest John Swift are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1883 Born, Santa Cruz, California
1908 Graduated Stanford University, Stanford, Calif.
1917 Enlisted with American Red Cross; attached to the 2nd Division, American Expeditionary Forces, France
1920 Deputy commissioner, American Red Cross, Montenegro
1920 1923 Business manager, and assistant to the European commissioner of the American Red Cross, Paris, France
1923 1931 Assistant to Colonel Ernest P. Bicknell, former Vice Chairman in Charge of Insular and Foreign Operations, American Red Cross
1927 Married Helen Griffin Swift
1929 Member, Red Cross China Famine Investigation Commission; visit to China
1930 Director, Red Cross hurricane relief, Dominican Republic
1931 Director, Red Cross earthquake relief, Nicaragua
1932 1936 Representative, League of Red Cross Societies on the International Relief Union’s Executive Committee Member, governing body, Nansen International Office for Refugees, League of Nations Secretary general, League of Red Cross Societies
1934 Vice president, International Red Cross Conference, Tokyo, Japan
1935 Chairman, American delegation to the International Air Ambulance Congress, Brussels, Belgium Secretary general, Third Pan-American Red Cross Conference, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil Vice Chairman in Charge of Insular and Foreign Operations, American Red Cross
1938 United States delegate, International Red Cross Conference, London, England
1941 Died, Washington, D. C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Ernest John Swift span the years 1908 to 2019, with the bulk of the material dating between 1920 and 1941. The collection documents Swift’s career as an administrator in the American Red Cross, as well as his personal life. The papers are primarily in English, with some material in French. The papers consist of eight series: Personal File, Correspondence, Clippings File, Publications, Travel File, Photographs and Negatives, Subject File, and Oversize.
The Personal File contains materials related to Swift’s personal life. It includes awards, certificates, and medals presented throughout his career, passports and other types of identification documents, calling cards and invitations, letters of condolence regarding Swift’s operation and death in 1941, and obituaries. This series also contains a scrapbook documenting Swift’s time as a student at Stanford University, as well as materials relating to Swift’s wedding and marriage to Helen Griffin Swift in 1927.
The Correspondence series includes both personal and business or Red Cross related materials.
The Clippings File contains copies of newspaper clippings regarding Swift’s personal life, career, accomplishments, and travels. It also includes some clippings regarding Helen Griffin Swift’s Red Cross volunteer work.
The Publications series consists of works and writings authored by Swift, publications produced by or relating to the Red Cross, and other miscellaneous publications.
The Travel File contains clippings, correspondence, photographs, and other materials related to Swift’s travels abroad, generally on Red Cross related business. Noteworthy materials include those relating to Swift’s 1934-1935 trip to Japan and India, for which he was vice president of the 1934 International Red Cross Conference in Tokyo, Japan. Additional materials in this series capture his relief and survey work for the Red Cross in Albania, Montenegro, the Dominican Republic, and China.
The Photographs and Negatives series features portraits of Swift, some Red Cross related images, and other miscellaneous or personal materials.
The Subject File documents some significant individuals or events in Swift’s life, including his brother, Percy Swift, as well as a series of letters from 1940-1941 detailing the efforts to get Mimi de Gielgud out of occupied France and to America in order to marry William van Doren Wright.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in eight series:
Personal File, 1908-1941
Correspondence, 1928-1940
Clippings File, 1929-1969
Publications, 1920-1941
Travel File, 1920-1935
Photographs and Negatives, 1920-1940
Subject File 1934-2019
Oversize, 1908-1940
Container List
- Personal File, 1908-1941 (Box 1-2)
  Awards and certificates, identification documents, letters of condolence regarding Swift's 1941 operation and death, obituaries, calling cards, invitations, miscellaneous material, and an oversize scrapbook.
  Arranged by subject.
  - Awards and certificates, 1908, 1919, 1927-1929, 1941 See also Oversize (Box 1)
  - Medals, undated See Oversize (Box OV 1)
  - Identification documents, 1913, 1923-1940 (Box 1)
  - First operation and death, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Letters sent at time of first operation, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Flowers sent at time of first operation, 1941 (Box 1)
    - Letters of condolence to Helen Griffin Swift, 1941, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Letters of condolence to Helen Griffin Swift from Red Cross personnel, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Obituaries, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Invitations, circa 1930s, 1938-1941 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook from time at Stanford University, circa 1908
    - Scrapbook, circa 1908 See Oversize (Box OV 1)
    - Loose items from scrapbook, circa 1908 (Box 2)
  - Wedding and marriage, 1927 (Box 2)
  - Miscellany, 1932-1934, undated (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1928-1940 (Box 2)
  Correspondence includes both personal and business-related materials.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, 1928-1940, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Clippings File, 1929-1969 (Box 2)
  Contains copies of newspaper clippings.
  - Clippings, 1927-1943, 1969 (Box 2)
- Publications, 1920-1941 (Box 3-4)
  Contains notes, speech materials, and printed matter.
  Arranged by type of material, and chronologically therein.
  - Speeches and writings, circa 1920s, 1921, 1928-1936, undated (Box 3)
  - Red Cross publications (Box 3)
    - Red Cross, 1928-1929, 1935-1941 (Box 3)
    - The Report of the American Red Cross Commission to China, 1929 (Box 3)
    - Review and Information Bulletin of the League of Red Cross Societies, 1932 (Box 3)
    - League of Red Cross Societies Monthly Bulletin, 1933 (Box 3)
    - League of Red Cross Societies Monthly Bulletin, 1934 (Box 4)
    - League of Red Cross Societies Monthly Bulletin, 1935 (Box 4)
    - League of Red Cross Societies Monthly Bulletin, 1936 (Box 4)
  - Other publications (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous publications, 1920, 1930-1940 (Box 4)
    - Fifty Years on the Quad: A Pictoral History of Stanford University, 1938 (Box 4)
- Travel File, 1920-1935 (Box 5)
  Contains clippings, correspondence, photographs, negatives, and miscellaneous material.
  - Teplena, Albania earthquake, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Belgium, 1935 (Box 5)
  - China, undated (Box 5)
  - England, circa 1930s (Box 5)
  - Greece, undated (Box 5)
  - Indonesia, undated (Box 5)
  - Japan, 1929 (Box 5)
  - Montenegro, 1920 (Box 5)
  - Santo Domingo hurricane, 1930 (Box 5)
  - Unknown, passenger lists, 1932-1937 (Box 5)
  - Conference Trip to Japan and India, 1934-1935 (Box 5)
    - Documents and papers, 1934-1935 (Box 5)
    - Calling cards (Japan), 1934 (Box 5)
    - Clippings, 1934-1935 (Box 5)
    - Photographs, 1934-1935 See also Photographs and Negatives, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Photographs (Japan), 1934-1935 (Box 5)
    - Photographs (India), 1934-1935 (Box 5)
- Photographs and Negatives, circa 1920-1940 (Box 6)
  Contains photographic prints and negatives.
  Arranged by subject. Photographs related to travel have been placed in the Travel File series by their related trip or geographic location.
  - Portraits, circa 1908, circa 1920-1940 See also Oversize (Box 6)
  - Puerto Rico Red Cross members with Ernest J. Swift, 1936 (Box 6)
  - Miscellany, circa 1930s, 1936, 1940, undated See also Oversize (Box 6)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 6)
  - Nitrate negatives, undated See also Travel File (Box 6)
- Subject File, 1934-2019 (Box 6)
  Contains clippings, photographs, correspondence, invitations, and other miscellaneous materials.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Gielgud, Lewis Evelyn, 1937 (Box 6)
  - Inventory to the Ernest John Swift Papers, 2019 (Box 6)
  - Mussolini, Benito, 1934 (Box 6)
  - Swift, Percy (brother), 1936, 1941-1943 (Box 6)
  - Wright, William van Doren and Mimi de Gielgud, 1940-1941 (Box 6)
- Oversize, circa 1908-1940 (Box OV 1)
  Contains medals, awards, photographs, and a scrapbook.
  Listed and described according to the series, containers, and folders from which the material was separated. The items are physically grouped and housed by size.
  - Personal File (Box OV 1)
    - Awards and certificates, 1919, 1941 (Container 1) (Box OV 1)
    - Medals, undated (Box OV 1)
    - Scrapbook, circa 1908 (Box OV 1)
  - Photographs and Negatives (Box OV 1)
    - Portraits, circa 1908, circa 1920-1940 (Container 6) (Box OV 1)
    - Film canister with contact sheet prints (“Christmas 1940” “Cape Cod MAR 1940”), circa 1940 (Container 6) (Box OV 1)